{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Ailsa McKay and Margunn Bjornholt [BYORN-holt] argued that a feminist worldview would\nhave avoided this event. Credit default swaps and institutions like commercial paper conduits\nand investment banks which make up the “shadow banking” system failed during this period,\nduring which AIG took the largest bailout in government history. The immediate cause of this\nevent was the collapse of Lehman Brothers. For 10 points, name this economic event which\ncaused US unemployment rates to rise to ten percent by 2009.",
      "answer": [
        "Great Recession",
        "2008 recession",
        "2008 financial crisis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Most members of this organization also participate in the Schengen [shane-gun] Area. This\norganization, which guarantees the single market, grew out of an agreement between the “inner\nsix” to trade coal and steel. This winner of the 2012 Nobel Peace Prize was created by the Treaty\nof Maastricht [mass-strict], but is currently threatened by the possible “Grexit.” For 10 points,\nname this organization of 28 member states across a namesake continent.",
      "answer": [
        "European Union",
        "EU"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man signed America’s first “stand your ground” law in 2005. He recently advised donors to contribute no more than 1 million dollars each to his PACs, and delivered a speech advocating a “right to rise” to the Detroit Economic Club in February. This man met his wife Columba while teaching English in Mexico. Secretary of State Katherine Harris led the 2000 presidential recount in the state this man governed. For 10 points, name this two-term governor of Florida and potential 2016 Republican candidate for President, the younger brother of George W.",
      "answer": "Jeb Bush"
    },
    {
      "question": "This tournament is officially named for a World War I aviator who put metal plates on his propeller to safely shoot a machine gun though it. Max Decugis [DEH-coo-gee] held a record eight singles titles at this event until that record was broken in 2014. The winningest champion at this second of the four Grand Slam events has won it in nine of the past ten years; that player is Spain’s Rafael Nadal [nuh-DALL]. For 10 points, name this only tennis Grand Slam tournament played on clay, which is held in continental Europe.",
      "answer": "French Open"
    },
    {
      "question": "The current leader of this political party declared that he had slept with “no more than 30 women” in an interview with GQ. After allegations of a drinking problem, Charles Kennedy stepped down as this party’s leader in 2006. In 2010, this party received 23 percent of the national vote, leading this party to form a governing coalition with David Cameron’s Conservative Party. For 10 points, name this party led by Nick Clegg, a political party in the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": "Liberal Democrats"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2003 example of this action led to the Supreme Court case LULAC v. Perry. Shaw v. Reno banned attempts to do this solely based on race, and it makes use of “packing” and “cracking.” This practice took its name from America’s fifth Vice President, who while as Governor of Massachusetts enacted a district whose elongated shape reminded opponents of a salamander. For ten points, name this practice of drawing electoral districts for partisan advantage.",
      "answer": "gerrymandering"
    },
    {
      "question": "Albert Schweitzer won the 1952 Nobel Peace Prize in part for building one of these institutions in Lambar´en´e, Gabon. The poor conditions in one of these buildings in Scutari led Isambard Kingdom Brunel to build a prefabricated one of these that was shipped to Renkioi during the Crimean War. One of these in Kunduz was attacked in 2015; that airstrike was requested by anti-Taliban forces and carried out by the US Air Force. For ten points, name these institutions built in warzones by Doctors Without Borders.",
      "answer": "hospital"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zia ul-Haq led a coup against one leader with this surname in Operation Fair Play. That leader with this surname was later arrested for the murder of Ahmed Kasuri and executed after a sham trial. That leader’s daughter was exiled on corruption charges for nine years before Pervez Musharraf granted her amnesty to run in 2007 elections; during that campaign, she was assassinated in Rawalpindi. For ten points, give this surname shared by Zulfikar Ali and Benazir, two Prime Ministers of Pakistan.",
      "answer": "Bhutto"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lieutenant Ryan Philips flew the speaker in this event to the USS Abraham Lincoln. This speech commemorated the removal of a “grave threat” and liberation of “an oppressed people,” though Donald Rumsfeld attempted to edit its language. This speech, given exactly eight years before the death of Osama bin Laden, announced the end of “major” combat operations in Iraq. For ten points, name this 2003 speech delivered by President George W. Bush in front of a banner displaying a controversially triumphant phrase.",
      "answer": "Mission Accomplished speech"
    },
    {
      "question": "Harry Trask captured three iconic photographs of Jock Semple accosting Katherine Switzer during one of these events, which Switzer entered under her initials. The testimony of John Faulkner helped discover Rosie Ruiz’s fraudulent claims about one of these sporting events. In 2012, one of these events was canceled in the aftermath of Superstorm Sandy. The traditional last event of the Summer Olympics is, for ten points, what sporting event, which was the site of a 2013 bombing in Boston?",
      "answer": "marathon"
    },
    {
      "question": "The execution of Mishaal, a member of this family, is depicted in the documentary Death of a Princess. The Battle of Sabila was a victory for one ruler from this house, leading to the defeat of the Ikhwan revolt. The economic well-being of this house is highly linked to the success of ARAMCO. The current head of this family, which supports the Wahhabi mission, became King in January 2015 after the death of his brother, Abdullah, in Riyadh. For ten points, name this Arab royal family led by King Salman, that rules over Saudi Arabia.",
      "answer": "House of Saud"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s rise to power was secured after the arrest of Osiel Cardenas. Early in his career, he broke an alliance with the Beltran Leyva, and his men accidentally killed the archbishop Juan Ocampos during a battle in Tijuana. This man prompted a federal reaction from Jose Calderon when his hit squad killed the head of the Juarez cartel in a shopping mall. After a second arrest, he escaped through a tunnel in July of 2015. For ten points, name this leader of the Sinaloa cartel who was interviewed by Sean Penn prior to his third arrest in 2016.",
      "answer": [
        "El Chapo",
        "Joaquin Archivaldo Guzm´an Loera"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This successor of John Smith was investigated after his party accepted loans in exchange for peerage appointments in the Cash for Honours scandal. This proponent of a “Third way” between capitalism and socialism mediated the Good Friday Agreement, which ended the Troubles in Northern Ireland. This Prime Minister backed George W. Bush’s invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq. For ten points, name this “New Labour” Prime Minister of Great Britain from 1997 to 2007.",
      "answer": "Tony Blair"
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to costs, Canadian Prime Minister John Diefenbaker scrapped one of these technologies, the Avro Arrow. One example of this technology, which crashed in a Paris exhibition in 1973, was the Tupolev Tu-144; the only other commercial use of this type of vehicle ended after a 2000 disaster, also in Paris. The Bell X-1, piloted by Chuck Yaeger, was the first example of, for ten points, what type of aircraft that can surpass Mach 1?",
      "answer": [
        "supersonic aircraft",
        "descriptions of an airplane that can break the speed of sound, including break Mach 1 before it’s mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2009, Karen Starko claimed that this event was exacerbated by the Surgeon General’s instruction to take aspirin. Woodrow Wilson nearly died in this event, which was first reported in the United States at Camp Funston in Fort Riley, Kansas. This event, which killed about five percent of the world’s population, was spread across the globe by soldiers near the end of World War I. For ten points, name this 1918 pandemic, commonly named for an Iberian country that didn’t censor the high death toll.",
      "answer": [
        "Spanish flu pandemic",
        "1918 flu before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After helping a Senator from this party pay back improper residency expenses, Chief of Staff Nigel Wright resigned his post in 2013. Another member of this party suggested introducing a “barbaric cultural practices tip line;” that politician, Kellie Leitch, is running for this party’s May 2017 leadership elections. Rona Ambrose is the current interim leader of this party after the October 2015 resignation of Stephen Harper. For ten points, name this Canadian political party that was removed from power by Justin Trudeau’s Liberals.",
      "answer": "Conservative Party of Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Cutter incident, vaccines of this virus were accidentally tainted with live virus. The inventor of the vaccine for this disease defended his decision to not patent it with the rebuttal “Could you patent the sun?” Wild cases of this disease in 2015 were reported only in Afghanistan and Pakistan. The “iron lung” was primarily used to assist sufferers of, for ten points, what viral disease whose vaccine was developed by Jonas Salk?",
      "answer": "poliomyelitis"
    },
    {
      "question": "After rising to power, this group banned the practice of “Bacha Bazi” between Pashtun warlords. Some former supporters of this group have defected to ISIs’s Khorasan Province branch. In March 2001, this group demolished giant, centuries-old statues of the Buddha in Bamiyan Province; later in 2001, this group was ousted from power by a NATO-led coalition. For ten points, name this Sunni terrorist group that operates in Afghanistan.",
      "answer": "Taliban"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bruce Hoffman’s “Inside [this activity]” describes the way in which it has been politicized by its victims. Alan Krueger’s 2007 study found that this activity was less likely to be carried out by those from an impoverished background. Examples of this activity include the Kunduz airlift in 2001, which was “state-sponsored” and led to a practitioner of this activity living in Abbottabad until 2011. For ten points, name this general term for intentional violence committed to achieve a political or ideological goal.",
      "answer": [
        "terrorism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2005, this figure offered his resignation to Larry Lucchino and walked out in a gorilla suit. In 2002, this man was hired for a job that had been turned down by Billy Beane, as described at the end of Moneyball. Tom Ricketts hired this man as President in 2011; with Jed Hoyer, this man brought Anthony Rizzo and Kris Bryant to Wrigley Field. For ten points, name this baseball executive who, as GM and President, ended the World Series droughts of both the Boston Red Sox and Chicago Cubs.",
      "answer": "Theo Epstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician with this surname campaigned with a Frankenstein doll that declared “You have nothing to fear with” that man. A woman with this surname won the Senate seat made available by the retirement of Jesse Helms; that woman with this married surname served as Secretary of Transportation under Ronald Reagan and Secretary of Labor under George W. Bush. For ten points, give this surname shared by North Carolina senator Elizabeth and a Kansas senator who lost the 1996 presidential election to Bill Clinton, Bob.",
      "answer": [
        "Dole",
        "Elizabeth Dole",
        "Bob Dole"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the originally planned climax of Men in Black II, these structures were to release a swarm of UFOs. A helicopter is caught in a web between these structures in an original trailer for the first Tobey Maguire Spiderman film. The 2008 film Man on Wire documents Philippe Petit’s illegal 1974 walk between these structures on a high-wire. Several early 21st century films edited out, for ten points, what Manhattan buildings that were attacked on September 11th?",
      "answer": [
        "World Trade Center 1 and/or 2",
        "Twin Towers and other descriptive answers of the two tallest bulidings in the WTC complex"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This political party was created by the Tamworth Manifesto, which aimed to distinguish it from the Duke of Wellington’s government. A leader of this party gave the Winds of Change speech in South Africa, signaling decolonization that included this party’s suppression of the Mau Mau Rebellion. A leader of this party nicknamed “Milk Snatcher” won a war over the Falklands Islands, and it allied with the DUP in 2016 under Theresa May. For ten points, name this British political party opposed by the Labour Party.",
      "answer": "Conservative Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. This policy was first reported in 2002 by The Hill and made news again in March 2017 in an Ashley Parker profile of the former Karen Batten. This policy’s ideological precedent is the Modesto Manifesto, leading some reporters to dub it the Billy Graham Rule. Critics of this policy, which includes rules regarding alcohol, work, and dining partners, argue that its application in the Governor’s office in Indianapolis and the White House constitutes sexual discrimination. For ten points, identify this personal code of the Vice President.",
      "answer": [
        "Mike Pence’s rules regarding behavior with women",
        "descriptions of Mike Pence’s rule against dining alone with women who aren’t his wife, Pence’s rule against working late with women, and/or Pence’s rule against attending events with alcohol without his wife being present"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A Frank Gehry-designed memorial to this man controversially plans to include a tapestry of stainless steel cables, which may depict peaceful imagery of France or Kansas. Statues planned for this man’s memorial include a group inspired by a photo of this man instructing the 101st Airborne Division on June 5th, 1944. In 2017, officials celebrated the groundbreaking of a long-planned memorial for, for ten points, what Supreme Commander of Allied Forces during World War II and US President?",
      "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an effort to encourage dental health, this leader encouraged his population to chew on bones because dogs do so. This leader renamed the month of September after his book Ruhnama, whose study is required to obtain a driver’s license in his country. This leader commissioned the construction of an Arch of Neutrality, which contained a golden statue of himself that rotated to face the sun in the city of Ashgabat. For ten points, name this totalitarian ruler of post-independence Turkmenistan from 1991 to his death in 2006.",
      "answer": "Saparmurat Niyazov or Turkmenbashi"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician from this state briefly ran for President in 2015 and condemned “immigration without assimilation” as “invasion.” Another politician from this state lost his 2015 bid for governor after a scandal involving him soliciting prostitutes; that man was David Vitter, who lost to a man who is now the only Democratic governor in the Deep South. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by John Bel Edwards, Bobby Jindal, and Kathleen Blanco, who served during Hurricane Katrina.",
      "answer": "Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "question": "At its 1931 opening, this bridge surpassed the Ambassador Bridge as the longest bridge in the world. This bridge, which was originally slated to be named the Knickerbocker Bridge, terminates at Fort Lee on one side. For a week in September 2013, two of this bridge’s three lanes were closed during rush hour traffic, a political punishment for Mark Sokolich for not supporting Chris Christie’s run for Governor of New Jersey. For ten points, name this bridge across the Hudson River.",
      "answer": [
        "George Washington Bridge",
        "GWB",
        "GW Bridge"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, a dramatization of the novel The Two Captains was broken up at the start of a terrorist attack. Civilian casualties in this city escalated after troops refused to tell doctors what type of chemical weapon they had used, leading to the death of 130 hostages. The Spetsnaz special forces indiscriminately used poison gas to end a hostage crisis in, for ten points, what city where Chechen terrorists occupied the Dubrovka Theater in 2002?",
      "answer": "Moscow"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2017, this state’s town of Cleveland settled a 52-year-long court case about the segregation of its public schools. This state passed a law banning felons from college admission, then charged a black applicant with false voter registration and convicted him in absentia on the same day. Ultimately, Robert F. Kennedy ordered U.S. Marshals to desegregate this state’s flagship university on the request of Governor Ross Barnett, who refused to do it without being coerced. For ten points, name this US state where James Meredith attended college in Oxford.",
      "answer": "Mississippi"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, market manipulation and megawatt laundering by traders under false names like “Death Star” and “Red Congo” led to rolling blackouts during the late 1990s and early 2000s. The murder of 15-year old Latasha Harlins by Soon Ja Du was one of the factors that increased racial tensions and led to the 1992 riots in this state. The successful recall of this state’s governor, Gray Davis, in 2003 led to the eventual election of actor Arnold Schwarzenegger. For ten points, name this state with the cities of Sacramento and Los Angeles.",
      "answer": "California 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "When analyzing this event, Slavoj Zizek [[SLAH-voh ZEE-zek]] applied Marxist and Lacanian analysis in the book Welcome to the Desert of the Real. This event inspired Borradori's [[boh-rah-DOH-rees]] dialogues with Habermas [[HAY-behr-mahs]] and Derrida [[DEH-rih-dah]], published under the title Philosophy in a Time of Terror. For ten points, name this terrorist attack, in which al-Qaeda agents destroyed two skyscrapers in New York.",
      "answer": "9/11 or September 11th"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2010, various artists proclaimed \"[Do this action] Day\" after Episode 201 of South Park was censored on Comedy Central. In 2015, Elton Simpson, along with an accomplice, attacked the Curtis Culwell Center, because the American Freedom Defense Initiative, or AFDI, did this. The AFDI had held the event because earlier that year, militants slaughtered artists at Charlie Hebdo who had done, for ten points, what haram action relating to the last prophet of Islam?",
      "answer": "Depicting Muhammad"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first provisional governor of this state, Wyandot [[WHY-an-dot]] leader William Walker, was unrecognized by the federal government. The first official governor of this state, David Butler, was impeached, and another governor, Silas Holcomb, ran on a combined Democratic/Populist ticket. William Jennings Bryan's brother, Charles Wayland, served as governor of this state, whose first female governor was Kay Orr. In 2015, Pete Ricketts became governor of, for ten points, what state which is governed from Lincoln?",
      "answer": "Nebraska"
    },
    {
      "question": "This proto-state intentionally opened the Nuaimiya Dam near Fallujah to deprive the Shia majority population of water. Late 2016 campaigns led to the loss of this organization’s stronghold of Mosul and its capital of Raqqa [[ROK-ah]]. Donald Trump approved of Operation Kayla Mueller, which killed this leader’s “Caliph” Abu Bakr Al- Baghdadi. For ten points, name this terrorist state which controlled portions of Iraq and Syria.",
      "answer": [
        "Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
        "ISIL",
        "Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
        "ISIS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At the beginning of this uprising, Robert Bealknap attempted mass arrests of its participants. A former employee of Geoffrey Chaucer, William Walworth, killed the leader of this revolt at the Battle of Smithfield. During this revolt, leaders Jack Straw and Wat Tyler planned to kill the sitting king, Richard II, in part due to high taxes which were levied on the underclass during the Hundred Years’ War. For ten points, name this 14th century English revolt, named for the agrarian class who rose up against the nobility.",
      "answer": [
        "Peasants’ Revolt",
        "Wat Tyler’s Revolt before mentioned",
        "Great Rising",
        "\"Rebellion\"",
        "\"Uprising\" in place of \"Revolt\" 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After a sack by these people, Pelagius [[peh-LAY-jyus]] and Caelestius [[seh-LEH- styus]] fled to North Africa, sparking the Pelagian controversy. One king of these people named Athaulf killed Sarus, and he and Sigeric were assassinated and succeeded by Wallia. Before marrying Constantius III, Theodosius the Great's daughter, Galla Placidia, was wed to a king of these people. These people, governed by the Terving and Balti dynasties, faced a Muslim invasion under Roderic. Alaric was a leader of, for ten points, what Gothic group who sacked Rome in 410?",
      "answer": "Visigoths 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "As HUD Secretary, this man urged Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac to buy loans from poor home owners, possibly causing the subprime mortgage crisis. This man noted that George Pataki \"held the leader's coat\" and that \"Cream rises to the top,\" referring to Rudy Giuliani. This man sued Rhode Island over its Quarantine policy, despite having his own lockdown policy. This man faces allegations of sexual harassment and admitted to covering up COVID-19 deaths at nursing homes. For ten points, name this governor of New York.",
      "answer": "Andrew Cuomo 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician responded abrasively to Jerry Falwell in response to his opposition regarding the appointment of Sandra Day O'Connor. In response to the Packard Commission, this man worked with William Flynt Nichols to create a bill that increased the power of the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. Despite being bolstered by Ronald Reagan's \"A Time for Choosing\" speech, this man was soundly defeated in the Election of 1964 by Lyndon B. Johnson. For ten points, name this Arizona politician, credited with laying the foundation for the Conservative Revolution.",
      "answer": "Barry Goldwater 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rebel Herero warriors were forced to cross this desert into British lands after the German Empire won the Battle of Waterberg in 1904. The homeland of the San [[SAHN]] People stretches across this desert, and the San are sometimes known as the “Bushmen\" of this desert. In 1997 the San and the Bakgalagadi were evicted from their land in this desert after De Beers determined the Gope diamond mines were valuable, but in 2006, the Botswana High Court ruled that their eviction from this desert was unlawful. For ten points, name this large desert of southern Africa.",
      "answer": "Kalahari Desert"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2010 redesign of this item removed the initials “VDB” from its front for the second time. During World War Two, these items were subject to a discoloring redox reaction when the chemistry-unaware Henry Morgenthau [[mohr-GEHN-thow]] authorized the addition of zinc to them. As a result, one of the most valuable examples of these items is the 1944 “steel wheat” variety. Since 2010 these items display a shield reading “e pluribus unum.” For ten points, name these coins which show Abraham Lincoln on the front.",
      "answer": "U.S. penny or pennies"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family wrote the book On the Art of the Cinema and ordered the kidnapping of film director Shin Sang-ok. Members of this family promote the ideology of \"military first\" or \"Songun\" and a quasi-religion called \"Juche\" [[JOO-cheh]]. A member of this family met with Dennis Rodman in 2013 and was rumored to be transferring power to his sister Yo-jong due to health issues in 2020. Dictators Il-sung, Jong-il, and Jong-un belong to, for ten points, what family that controls North Korea?",
      "answer": "Kim family"
    },
    {
      "question": "The lack of convictions surrounding this figure's death led to its site being dubbed \"The Freestate of Tallahatchie\" by the Chicago Defender. Married white woman Carolyn Bryant likely lied that this Black teenager whistled at her. This figure names a 2008 \"Act\" sponsored by John Lewis which aimed to attempt to solve cold cases of violence against Black victims prior to the 1970s. A mid-1950s mob in Mississippi murdered, for ten points, which 14 year old Black teen, whose death galvanized the Civil Rights movement?",
      "answer": "Emmett Till or Emmett Louis Till"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In Israel, the Ale Yarok party is best known for its platform on this substance. Rick Steves\nargued that many current laws about this substance affect “people who are arrested and cited,\nwho are poor,” not “rich white guys” who enjoy it. The U.S. House of Representatives passed a\n2014 bill that prevented welfare funds going to states that defy the FDA and DEA and have\nlegalized this substance. For 10 points, name this plant-based drug now legal in DC, Washington,\nand Colorado.",
        "answer": [
          "marijuana",
          "cannabis",
          "weed",
          "pot",
          "grass"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A study about this chemical in cannabis showed it to treat symptoms of multiple\nsclerosis. It is also responsible for the increase in appetite and food consumption in humans.",
        "answer": [
          "THC",
          "tetrahydrocannabinol"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "As governor, this man stirred controversy with an unpopular vehicle registration tax, and he\nwas known as the “Boy Governor.” During his time as president, this man’s personal attorney\nVince Foster committed suicide. This man was attacked for his involvement in the “travelgate”\nand “Whitewater” scandals. For 10 points, name this former Arkansas governor who was\ninaugurated as president in 1993.",
        "answer": [
          "William Jefferson Bill Clinton",
          "Bill Clinton",
          "Clinton"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Whitewater investigation was headed by this man, who later produced a report\nalleging that Clinton had lied about an extramarital affair.",
        "answer": [
          "Ken Starr",
          "Starr",
          "Kenneth Winston Starr"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Coronation glyphs from this culture are found on Altar Q at the site of Copan. Religious traditions among these people based on the k’atun cycle are recorded in folding books called chilam balaam. This culture’s most notable creation includes a “Long Count” system and is more accurate than a Gregorian counterpart. For 10 points, what Mesoamerican culture created a calendar that predicted the world’s doom in 2012?",
        "answer": "Maya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which great ruler of Palenque had the longest-known reign in Western hemisphere history?",
        "answer": "Pacal the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two men shared this award in 1997 for work on a formula used to calculate values for put and call options. Another winner of this award blamed inefficiencies in distribution for causing world hunger in his Poverty and Famines. In addition to Myron Scholes, Robert Merton, and Amartya Sen, this award has been won by Milton Friedman and 27 other University of Chicago thinkers. In 2008, Paul Krugman won, for ten points, what award, given annually in Sweden for work in a field that studies, among other things, consumption, production, and money?",
        "answer": "Nobel Memorial Prize in Economics or Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Science in Memory of Alfred Nobel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Krugman is a columnist and blogger for this newspaper, known as the “Grey Lady.”",
        "answer": "The New York Times"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to Richard Clarke, one holder of this position was to be ousted by Operation Orient Express. A former holder of this position was running for President of Austria in 1985 when his service in the Wehrmacht was uncovered. Another holder of this position died in a plane crash while en route to resolve the Katanga crisis. Kurt Waldheim and Dag Hammarskjold [hammar-sk’yold] have held, and Ban Ki-moon currently holds, for ten points, what position as leader of the United Nations?",
        "answer": "Secretary-General of the United Nations"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This diplomat from Ghana preceded Ban Ki-moon as Secretary-General and briefly served as a special envoy to Syria in 2012.",
        "answer": "Kofi Annan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader’s government accused five Bulgarian nurses of spreading HIV in a children’s hospital. This leader held the position of “Brother Leader and Guide of the Revolution.” In 2003, this leader accepted responsibility for the bombing of Pan Am Flight 103. This leader, who rose to power in 1969 after overthrowing King Idris, was overthrown by the National Transitional Council and killed during the Battle of Sirte during the Arab Spring. For ten points, name this colonel and long-time dictator of Libya.",
        "answer": "Muammar Gaddafi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "270 people were killed due to the 1988 explosion of Pan Am Flight 103 over Lockerbie in this country.",
        "answer": "Scotland"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Pintupi Nine were a group of these people, another group of which helped John King survive the Burke and Willis expedition. The Pilbara strike was led by these people, whose land rights were recognized in the Mabo case, which overturned the decision made in the Gove lands rights case. This group “scarred” trees for their bark to create coolamons. In 2008, Kevin Rudd apologized to these people for his country’s government removing their children from their care. For ten points, name these original inhabitants of Australia.",
        "answer": [
          "Australian Aborigines",
          "equivalents like indigenous people of Australia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term refers to the children taken from Aboriginal families and raised by white foster families in the 20th century.",
        "answer": "Stolen Generation or stolen children"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was first elected as part of the Fifth Republic Movement. This leader called Vincente Fox “the puppy dog of the empire.” During an Ibero-American Summit, King Juan Carlos I asked this leader “Why don’t you shut up?” This leader’s funding led to the establishment of the TeleSUR TV network. He’s not Evo Morales, but this leader promoted “Socialism in the 21st century” as part of his Bolivarian Revolution. For ten points, name this socialist President of Venezuela during most of the 2000s.",
        "answer": "Hugo Chavez"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chavez was succeeded by this man as president of Venezuela. The Popular Will Party staged protests against this leader in 2014.",
        "answer": "Nicolas Maduro"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Participants in these events are advised to “confess your sins” and to “leave a note for your next of kin;” those tips are delivered, just before John Laurens wins one of these events, in a series of “Commandments” inspired by a Notoroius B.I.G. track. Participants in these events are advised by their seconds and count off ten paces. For ten points, name this violent events, one of which is depicted in a 2015 musical involving Aaron Burr and Alexander Hamilton.",
        "answer": [
          "duels",
          "additional information, including descriptions of duels in the musical Hamilton"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Laurens dueled Charles Lee for criticizing George Washington, which Lee did after being court-martialed for disobeying orders at this June 1778 battle in New Jersey. Contrary to Hamilton’s lyrics, far less than “a thousand soldiers [died] in 100-degree heat” at this battle.",
        "answer": "Battle of Monmouth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This play’s line “I will save you tomorrow... from yourself I will save you” is often omitted because its Act 2, Scene 2 is usually not performed. Liam Neeson starred in a 2002 revival of this play, in which a “poppet” is created by Mary Warren. After asking for “more weight,” Giles Corey is crushed to death in this play. John Proctor is hanged at the end of, for ten points, what Red Scare allegory set during the Salem Witch Trials, a play written by Arthur Miller?",
        "answer": "The Crucible"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Arthur Miller play, Incident at this location, is set before a World War II interrogation. Philippe Petain was among the leaders of its puppet government.",
        "answer": [
          "Vichy",
          "Incident at Vichy",
          "Vichy France"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party launched the Chakrabarti Inquiry after several of its own members made anti-Semitic statements. CCTV footage showed this party’s leader walking past available train seats in order to show that rail privatization has led to a shortage of space. Owen Smith lost this party’s 2016 leadership election, triggered after a vote of no confidence following Brexit. For ten points, name this party led by Jeremy Corbyn, the current opposition party in the British House of Commons.",
        "answer": "Labour Party of the United Kingdom"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Owen Smith received support for the Labour leadership from this former leader of the Labour Party. He stepped down after the Tories won the 2015 general elections.",
        "answer": "Ed Miliband"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country indicted Tatsuya Kato for his reporting of the aftermath of a 2013 disaster that killed 304 people, including numerous students from Danwon High School. Wikileaks released a 2007 diplomatic cable in which this country’s current president was accused of being under the control of a “Rasputin” like figure. Choi Soon-sil faces charges of influencing Park Geun-Hye, the president of, for ten points, what Asian country where protesters against Park flooded the streets of Seoul?",
        "answer": "South Korea or Republic of Korea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 2013 disaster was the sinking of this ferry, which capsized after a sharp turn off the southwest coast of South Korea.",
        "answer": "MV Sewol"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. In 2010, Ronnie Lee Gardner opted to undergo this action in accordance with his “Mormon heritage.” Eddie Adams captured a photograph of this action about to be performed against Nguyen Van Lem, a Communist assassin, in 1968 in the streets of Saigon by a police general. When this action is done by a group of people, some may be randomly given blanks to diffuse the personal responsibility. For ten points, name this violent act of punishment often performed by a firing squad.",
        "answer": [
          "shooting the condemned",
          "descriptions of killing someone with a gun, including elaborations mentioning any specific bodily target",
          "equivalents for killing, like execution",
          "any specifically named firearm for gun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A famous photograph of an Execution of a German Communist in Munich appears to be staged, as most of the Freikorps firing squad is ill-prepared to fire. The photo was taken in January 1919 during this general strike in post-World War I Germany, which ended with the executions of Rosa Luxemburg and Karl Liebknecht.",
        "answer": "Spartacist Uprising Revolt, Rebellion, War, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2006, 11 people in this country’s town of Ishaqi in Balad province were killed and their house blown up; cables released by Wikileaks indicate that U.S. forces were responsible for that incident. Camp Speicher, an air force base in this country’s city of Tikrit, was attacked by ISIS in 2014, killing over 1,500 Shia cadets. In 2007, George W. Bush ordered a “surge” of troops into, for ten points, what Middle Eastern country invaded by U.S. forces in 2003?",
        "answer": "Iraq"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Employees of this private security company, which has since been renamed XE Services and Academi, killed 17 people in the 2007 Nisour Square massacre in Baghdad; four of its guards were convicted of manslaughter or murder.",
        "answer": "Blackwater"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man secured power after hiring North Korea to train the paramilitary Fifth Brigade, which he used to purge political enemies during the Gukurahundi period. This man’s removal of vice president EmersonMnangagwaledtospeculationthatheplannedtonamehisunpopularwifeGraceashissuccessor, leading to his removal in a 2017 coup. This man’s reign was marked by an inflation rate that peaked at 100,000 percent in 2008. For ten points, name this longtime ruler of Zimbabwe.",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mugabe rose to prominence in a civil war against this man, who issued the Unilateral Declaration of Independence.",
        "answer": "Ian Smith"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This institution was created after Charles Lindbergh, Sr. helped inspire the creation of the Pujo Committee. James Reed’s decisive vote helped create this institution, resulting in his home state of Missouri being granted two of its 12 major branches. This agency was created by a bill introduced by Robert Owen and Carter Glass, each of whom chaired a congressional Banking and Currency Committee. A 1913 act created, for ten points, what central banking system of the US?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve System"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Janet Yellen as chair of the Federal Reserve in 2018, despite not having a PhD in Economics.",
        "answer": "Jerome Powell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2015, 30 people were detained in this country during the “709” crackdown on lawyers. This country’s government has been accused of harvesting organs from members of a religious group symbolized by a Dharma Wheel. An activist from this country was awarded the 2010 Nobel Prize while imprisoned for the crime of “Inciting subversion of state power.” The Uyghur [wee-gur] minority has suffered persecution in, for ten points, what country whose government cracked down on the Tiananmen Square protests in Beijing?",
        "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Buddhist-inspired religious movement, whose emblem is the Dharma Wheel, has been persecuted in China since the mid-1990s. Li Hongzhi, who lives in exile in New York, was one of the founders of this movement.",
        "answer": "Falun Gong or Falun Dafa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This company was criticized for deciding not to remove footage of the Lac-M´egantic disaster, one of the deadliest train derailments in Canadian history, as stock footage in one of its 2018 films. A company called “Qwikster” was to be spunoff from this company in 2011, but CEO Reed Hastings quickly changed course. Programs like Narcos and the American version of House of Cards were produced by, for ten points, what streaming service that released Bird Box in 2018?",
        "answer": "Netflix"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Narcos was a three-season drama set in Colombia about this drug kingpin, who was killed in 1993.",
        "answer": "Pablo Escobar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2000, a leader of this ethnicity was assassinated while filling out a football betting slip in the lobby of the Intercontinental Hotel. Members of this ethnicity formed the White Eagles and the Volunteer Guard, the latter of which was better known as Arkan’s Tigers. The Scorpions, who were of this ethnicity, wereledbyRatkoMladic[m’lah-ditch]inperpetratingtheSrebrenica[sreh-breh-neetzah]massacreagainst Bosniaks in the Yugoslav Wars. For ten points, name this Southern Slavic ethnic group, the majority ethnic group in Belgrade.",
        "answer": [
          "Serbs",
          "Serbians, despite minor differences between the terms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After being indicted for war crimes, this first President of Republika Srpska was on the run for 12 years before being arrested while disguised in Belgrade. This man and Ratko Mladic were convicted of the Srebrenica massacre.",
        "answer": "Radovan Karadzic , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s press secretary, Andr´e Singer, transformed this man’s name into a term for a no-conflict, stable ideology. After leaving office at the end of 2010, this man’s appointment as Chief of Staff under his successor was blocked by Gilmar Mendes [zheel-mar men-des]. A $1.1 million apartment was found to have been given to this man as a bribe as part of an investigation known as Operation Car Wash. This former leader of the Workers’ Party was jailed after being convicted on money laundering charges in 2017. For ten points, name this predecessor of Dilma Rousseff as President of Brazil.",
        "answer": [
          "Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva",
          "either",
          "both underlined parts"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This judge sentenced Lula da Silva and many other criminals investigated by Operation Car Wash. In 2018, this man accepted the post of Justice Minister under Jair Bolsonaro.",
        "answer": "Sergio Moro"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this war, the central government outlined a campaign based on the Marshall Plan that called for the “3 Rs” of reconstruction, rehabilitation, and reconciliation. A successful invasion of the port of Calabar occurred during this war’s Operation Tiger Claw. The largest civilian airlift in history was carried out during this war, in which Joseph Achuzie failed to repel an invasion at Port Harcourt. Muhammadu Buhari commanded a battalion during, for ten points, what 1967-70 war over a secessionist Igbo state in Nigeria?",
        "answer": "Biafran War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Early in his career, this man commanded a division during the Biafran War. After this man escaped death in a failed 1976 coup, he led as the head of a military government for three years; he was then democratically elected president in 1999 and 2003.",
        "answer": "Olusegun Obasanjo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician published the autobiography Why Not the Best? shortly before declaring to run in the primary elections. During his term, this President oversaw the evacuation of Love Canal and the passing of the Superfund law. This man’s namesake doctrine sanctioned the USSR for their invasion of Afghanistan, and he boycotted the Moscow Summer Olympics shortly before he lost re-election. The 2002 Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to, for ten points, what US President who was succeeded by Ronald Reagan?",
        "answer": "James Earl “Jimmy” Carter, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Carter and his wife Rosalynn have increased public awareness of this Georgia-based charity that uses a volunteer labor force to build housing around the world.",
        "answer": "Habitat for Humanity International"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After land mines and missiles were found at Ascot House, this man dismissed another leader as “a cobra in the house.” The Gukhurahundi massacres, whose name means “the early rain that washes away the chaff,” were carried out by this leader’s army. In the 2013 elections, this opponent of Joshua Nkomo claimed he would “fight like a wounded animal.” After sacking Emmerson Mnangagwa, this man was placed under house arrest. For ten points, name this leader of Zimbabwe from 1980 to 2017.",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mugabe led this Zimbabwean political party, which shared power for the first time in history in 2008 after Morgan Tsvangirai’s [chang-ee-rai’s] Movement for Democratic Change won 100 seats in parliament.",
        "answer": "ZANU-PF"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2004, Dorval Airport was renamed to honor this leader, whose government supported the construction of Mirabel Airport in the 1970s in the hopes of phasing out Dorval. This leader signed the Official Languages Act, which supported both English and French in federal government services; that act was signed a year after this man succeeded Lester Pearson. This man served as Prime Minister for over 15 years, the third longest tenure in Canadian history. For ten points, name this Canadian politician, the father of modern Prime Minister Justin.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mirabel International Airport served this major Canadian city for nearly 30 years before transitioning into a cargo-only airport in 2004. Mirabel was unpopular because it is a decidedly long drive away from the island in the Saint Lawrence River on which this city was built.",
        "answer": "Montreal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Rick Kahn delivered a partisan eulogy for a politician from this state who died in a plane crash days before an election against Norm Coleman. That politician, Paul Wellstone, was replaced on this state’s Senate ballot in 2000 by a man who had earlier criticized Gary Hart during a presidential primary with the slogan “where’s the beef?” This state and Washington, DC were the only electoral votes carried by this state’s native son in 1984. For ten points, name this home state of Walter Mondale.",
        "answer": "Minnesota"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This New York representative ran on the Democratic ticket with Mondale in the 1984 election.",
        "answer": "Geraldine Ferraro"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Randolph Hearst and the DuPont family may have conspired to pass a tax on this product that was overturned in Leahy v. U.S.. The LaGuardia Committee studied this product’s effect on juvenile delinquency. The MORE Act, which passed the House Judiciary Committee in 2019, authorizes expungement of past convictions for this product. Colorado and Washington were the first states to legalize the recreational use of, for ten points, what drug whose psychoactive properties are derived from THC and which is the subject of the propaganda film Reefer Madness?",
        "answer": [
          "marijuana",
          "cannabis",
          "colloquial terms such as pot, weed, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2019, Illinois became the eleventh state to legalize recreational marijuana, completing a campaign promise by this man who succeeded Bruce Rauner as governor in 2018.",
        "answer": "Jay Robert “JB” Pritzker"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler of a kingdom in this modern country, Yalamber, had his head cut off by Lord Krishna according to the Mahabharata. The first two dynasties of this country were the Kirata and the Licchavi. Unification of this country occurred under Prithvi Narayan Shah, who conquered Nuwakot and created the Gorkha Kingdom. In 2001, Prince Diprendra killed 9 members of this country’s royal family. For ten points, name this Himalayan nation where pro-democracy protests took place in 2006 in Kathmandu.",
        "answer": "Nepal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Birendra as the last king of Nepal. In 2006, he restored the parliament, which abolished the monarchy in 2008.",
        "answer": "Gyanendra Bir Bikram Shah Dev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman, who organized a volunteer drive to assist the victims of the Ancash earthquake in Peru, was the first First Lady to give an address at a Republican nominating convention. This woman, who once remarked “I know only what I read in the newspapers,” “doesn’t have a mink coat,” but “does have a respectable Republican cloth coat” according to a defensive speech given by her husband. This woman earned the nickname “Madame Ambassador” for her frequent international trips, including a notable visit to China. For ten points, name this successor to Lady Bird Johnson whose husband resigned after the Watergate Scandal.",
        "answer": "Thelma Catherine “Pat” Nixon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This reporter praised Pat Nixon as the “warmest First Lady I covered.” This woman, who served as a White House correspondent from 1961 to 2010 and uniquely had a personally assigned seat in the front row of the White House Briefing Room, abruptly retired after making antisemitic remarks.",
        "answer": "Helen Thomas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Several iterations of this entity were criticized for being political statements against the Bush Administration. A member of the Swedish parliament nominated Adolf Hitler for one of these in 1939. In 2010, a Chinese group created a competitor to this prize named for Confucius as a response to one of these being given to Liu Xiaobo [[LOO SHAO-BOH]]. First given to Henri Dunant [[doo-NANH]] and Frédéric Passy in 1901, for ten points, what is this award, one of five established in the will of a Swedish industrialist?",
        "answer": "Nobel Peace Prize"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This organization, the food-assistance branch of the U.N., was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2020 for its efforts to feed those affected by conflict.",
        "answer": [
          "World Food Programme",
          "WFP"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The killing of three settlers by this tribe in the town of Cascade led to U.S. army skirmishes during the Sheepeater War. William Clark nicknamed a child from this tribe \"Pompey\" and took care of him after his mother’s death. A member of this tribe, whose leaders included Pocatello, was married to French-Canadian trader Toussaint Charbonneau [[SHAR-ben-no]] and successfully traveled through the Bozeman Pass while serving as a guide with the Corps of Discovery. For ten points, name this Idaho tribe, whose members have included Sacagawea.",
        "answer": "Shoshone or Shoshoni"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sacagawea began appearing on the U.S. dollar coin beginning in 2000, replacing this women's rights activist.",
        "answer": "Susan B. Anthony 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the location of the Cassette Scandal in which Leonid Kuchma [[KOOCH-mah]] was implicated in the kidnapping of a journalist. The Pora! Youth demonstrated in this country in the Orange Revolution, which led to the presidency of Viktor Yushchenko [[yoosh-CHEN-koh]]. Starting in 2014, this country faced separatists in the Donbass and Donetsk People's Republic, and its lands in the Crimean Peninsula were annexed by Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this neighbor of Russia.",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of a special agreement at this 1945 conference held in Crimea, Ukraine and Byelorussia became two of the founding members of the United Nations.",
        "answer": "Yalta Conference"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician's father resigned his Senate seat in 2002 to become his state's governor and appointed this person to fill the seat. In 2010, this senator ran a successful write-in campaign after being defeated in the Republican primary by Joe Miller. Donald Trump promised to campaign against this politician in the 2022 midterms in retaliation for her vote to convict during his second impeachment. In 2018, this politician was the only Republican senator to not vote for Brett Kavanaugh's confirmation. For ten points, name this female senator from Alaska.",
        "answer": "Lisa Ann Murkowski"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Along with Murkowski and Ben Sasse, this other senator was the only Republican not from a swing state to vote for Trump's conviction in his second impeachment trial. This senator has served alongside John Kennedy representing Louisiana.",
        "answer": "William \"Bill\" Cassidy 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Oil workers in this state were depicted in the documentary The Overnighters. The opening of the Parshall oil field led to an oil boom in this state from 2006 to 2014 which included horizontal drilling and damaging hydraulic fracking. The 1997 Red River Flood severely damaged this state's city of Grand Forks. This state was formerly home to the \"divorce capital\" of the Midwest at its largest city of Fargo. For ten points, name this upper Midwest U.S. state.",
        "answer": "North Dakota"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "North Dakota's oil boom occurred due to the development of this oil shale formation which occupies some 200 thousand square miles across North Dakota, Montana, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba.",
        "answer": "Bakken ] Formation"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "It's not Cro-Magnons, but these people are hypothesized to have created the oldest known musical instrument, the \"Divje Babe [[div-YEH BAH-beh]] Flute.\" This species' namesake 2010 genome project revealed that non-African homo sapiens often intermixed with this people's \"Altai Mountain\" branch. A valley in Germany names, for ten points, which extinct human species known for protruding foreheads and comparatively shorter limbs than modern humans?",
        "answer": [
          "Neanderthals",
          "Homo sapiens neanderthalensis"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other species of archaic human are believed to be the ancestor of Neanderthals, Denisovans, and modern humans? They were likely the first archaic humans to spread throughout Eurasia.",
        "answer": "Homo erectus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This president repealed the Glass-Steagall Act, citing it was \"no longer appropriate.\" This president signed a law mandating background checks on firearms purchases, the Brady Bill, and dealt with \"Troopergate\" when several officers from his home state alleged they had arranged romantic liaisons for him. This president's Whitewater scandals merged with another scandal in which he claimed to have not had \"sexual relations with that woman.\" For ten points, name this Democratic president during the 1990s who was impeached for perjury for lying about his affair with Monica Lewinsky.",
        "answer": "Bill Clinton or William Jefferson Clinton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clinton nominated two Supreme Court justices, Stephen Breyer, and this late justice who died in September 2020.",
        "answer": [
          "Ruth Bader Ginsberg",
          "RBG"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man earned the ire of the internet after a tweet resurfaced of him saying, \"Nothing sadder than a hot person in a wheelchair\" in reference to disability activist Rebecca Cokely. After a streak of early 2000s television appearances, this man was approached by Harry Reid and Chuck Schumer to run for the U.S. Senate from Utah. This man defeated both Brad Rutter and James Holzhauer in a special tournament dubbed \"The Greatest of All Time.\" The longest streak in Jeopardy! history is held by, for ten points, which game show contestant?",
        "answer": "Ken Jennings or Kenneth Wayne Jennings III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What computer system developed by IBM defeated both Rutter and Jennings in a special series of Jeopardy!, winning the million dollar prize?",
        "answer": "Watson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Largo citizen Robert Scott Palmer was given a 63 month sentence for participation in this event following his assault of an officer with a wooden plank. A blue suit worn by Representative Andy Kim was donated to the Smithsonian after a photo of him in it cleaning litter in the wake of this event went viral. Mitch McConnell openly condemned this event as a \"failed insurrection.\" A pro-Trump mob aimed to overturn the election by attempting to seize the title legislative house in, for ten points, which January 2021 attack?",
        "answer": [
          "2021 United States Capitol Attack",
          "\"Insurrection\"",
          "\"Riot\" in place of \"Attack\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Conspiracy theorists claimed that the Capitol Riot was a false flag operation by which decentralized movement that opposes far right politics?",
        "answer": [
          "Antifa",
          "Antifacists"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A state named for this body of water was founded at the site where a mouse deer was seen outwitting a dog by Parameswara [[pah-rah-mes-WAH-rah]], and employed the Orang Laut people as a militia. Afonso de Albuquerque built the A Famosa fortress to establish Portuguese rule over this waterway, whose narrowing at the Phillip Channel may be relieved by a canal through the Isthmus of Kra. A spike in piracy in the early 2000s plagued, for ten points, what strait through which cargo ships pass between the Indian and Pacific Oceans?",
        "answer": "Straits of Malacca"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Java-based thalassocratic empire controlled the Straits of Malacca and was the last major Hindu power in the region before the rise of the Demak Sultanate?",
        "answer": "Majapahit Empire or Kerajaan Majapahit"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2021 this country pardoned three women who received 30-year sentences after undergoing medically necessary abortions. This country, which receives major law enforcement funding from the U.S. under the Territorial Control Plan, attempted to depose its Attorney General and five supreme court justices in May 2021. The New Ideas party of Nayib Bukele [[boo-KEH-leh]] won large 2021 electoral victories in, for ten points, what country which has recently decreased its notorious murder rate driven by the MS-13 gang?",
        "answer": "Republic of El Salvador or Republica de El Salvador"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2021 El Salvador, which has not printed its own money since 2001, rolled out the government-run \"Chivo\" service to support the introduction of which currency as legal tender alongside the U.S. dollar?",
        "answer": "Bitcoin"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ISRAELI POLITICS",
      "prompt": "In the State of Israel, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the coastal city that the United Nations recognizes as the capital of Israel?",
          "answer": "Tel Aviv"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the holy city where the Israeli legislature actually meets?",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "The current Prime Minister of Israel, re-elected in January 2013?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Netanyahu"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 120-seat parliament that is the national legislature of Israel?",
          "answer": "Knesset"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the Israeli intelligence service which has been known to kidnap or assassinate terrorists in other countries?",
          "answer": "Mossad"
        },
        {
          "question": "The President of the Palestinian National Authority since 2005 who frequently negotiates with the Israeli Prime Minister?",
          "answer": "Mahmoud Abbas"
        },
        {
          "question": "The right-wing party that the current Prime Minister belongs to?",
          "answer": "Likud"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the Israeli military, which many Israelis are drafted into?",
          "answer": "Israeli Defense Forces"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ominous Warnings",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Roman dictator killed, as predicted, on the Ides of March?",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "2005 hurricane that Robert Ricks predicted would make most of New Orleans “UNINHABITABLE FOR WEEKS...PERHAPS LONGER.”",
          "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
        },
        {
          "question": "2012 “superstorm” that flooded New Jersey and New York, shortly after the NWS begged “IF YOU ARE RELUCTANT [to evacuate], THINK OF YOUR LOVED ONES”.",
          "answer": "Hurricane or Superstorm Sandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "German leader whose abdication was predicted 20 years in advance by Otto von Bismarck.",
          "answer": "Kaiser Wilhelm II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Physicist who quoted “I am become death, the destroyer of worlds” after the Trinity nuclear test.",
          "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Daughter of Priam who was given the power of prophecy, but the curse of never being believed.",
          "answer": "Cassandra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet premier who refused to mobilize in spite of intelligence about Operation Barbarossa.",
          "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tragedy coincidentally foreshadowed by Morgan Robertson’s 1898 novella Futility.",
          "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Middle Eastern Leaders",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dictator who ruled Iraq during the Persian Gulf War and was overthrown in 2003.",
          "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Prime Minister of Israel.",
          "answer": "Benjamin Netanyahu"
        },
        {
          "question": "”Iron Lady” of Israel, its fourth Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "Golda Meir"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current President of Turkey.",
          "answer": "Recep Tayyip Erdogan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former President of Egypt who was deposed in 2013 after claiming unlimited power to undo the work of his predecessor, Hosni Mubarak.",
          "answer": "Mohamed Morsi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former President of Iran who spoke to the UN General Assembly in 2010, questioning whether the U.S. government committed the 9/11 attacks.",
          "answer": "Mahmoud Ahmadinejad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current King of Jordan, who succeeded his father, King Hussein, in 1999.",
          "answer": "Abdullah II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Vice President of Iraq, who served as Prime Minister for 8 years after the end of the Transitional Government in 2006.",
          "answer": "Nouri al-Maliki"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The New Deal",
      "prompt": "Names or abbreviations acceptable. Which New Deal agency or program...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Built hydroelectric dams in Tennessee?",
          "answer": "Tennessee Valley Authority or TVA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paid its first monthly retirement benefit to Ida May Fuller in January 1941?",
          "answer": "Social Security Administration or SSA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Restored faith in banks by insuring the money held in certain accounts?",
          "answer": "Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation or FDIC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Developed natural resources by employing young, unemployed men, who sent most of their wages back home?",
          "answer": "Civilian Conservation Corps or CCC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Employed millions in public works projects under Harry Hopkins?",
          "answer": "Works Progress Administration or WPA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Enforces regulations on financial trading, including 2002’s Sarbanes-Oxley Act?",
          "answer": "Securities and Exchange Commission or SEC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paid farmers to reduce their production, thereby increasing prices?",
          "answer": "Agricultural Adjustment Act or AAA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discriminated against African-Americans by “redlining,” a process that prevented mortgage investment in minority areas?",
          "answer": "Federal Housing Administration or FHA"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Abraham Lincoln’s Cabinet...",
      "prompt": "Name the abraham lincoln’s cabinet......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Included how many positions? This number also follows “four score” in the Gettysburg Address.",
          "answer": "seven"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included three former Republican rivals in what year’s Presidential election, which Lincoln won?",
          "answer": "Election of 1860"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the subject of Team of Rivals, a 2005 work that won what annual prize for writing bestowed by Columbia University?",
          "answer": "Pulitzer Prize for History"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inspired what American historian to write Team of Rivals?",
          "answer": "Doris Kearns Goodwin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included what Secretary of State who purchased Alaska?",
          "answer": "William Seward"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included what Secretary of War who Andrew Johnson couldn’t fire due to the Tenure of Office Act?",
          "answer": "Edwin Stanton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included what Secretary of the Treasury, who resigned in 1864 and became Chief Justice?",
          "answer": "Salmon P. Chase"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included Montgomery Blair in what position, no longer in the Cabinet?",
          "answer": "Postmaster General"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nobel Peace Prize Winners",
      "prompt": "Given the year of the award and a clue, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1993: Former South African prisoner who was a co-recipient with F.W. de Klerk.",
          "answer": "Nelson Mandela"
        },
        {
          "question": "2014: Pakistani teenage activist for education of girls.",
          "answer": [
            "Malala Yousafzai",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2001: Global diplomatic organization then led by co-winner, Secretary General Kofi Annan.",
          "answer": "United Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "1991: Burmese democratic activist, under house arrest at the time of the award.",
          "answer": "Aung San Suu Kyi"
        },
        {
          "question": "2011: Liberian President and women’s rights activist.",
          "answer": "Ellen Johnson Sirleaf"
        },
        {
          "question": "1901: organization founded by one of the first winners, Henry Dunant.",
          "answer": "International Committee of the Red Cross"
        },
        {
          "question": "2015: Country where a National Dialogue Quartet worked for democratic change after the Jasmine Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Tunisia",
            "Tunisian National Dialogue Quartet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "2010: Chinese activist and supporter of Charter 08, who remains a political prisoner.",
          "answer": "Liu Xiaobo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alaska",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colonial power that ruled Alaska before selling it to the United States.",
          "answer": "Russian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late 19th century event that brought an influx of immigrants into Alaska, begun by a discovery by Soapy Smith.",
          "answer": "Klondike Gold Rush or Yukon Gold Rush"
        },
        {
          "question": "US Secretary of State who purchased Alaska for 7.2 million dollars.",
          "answer": [
            "William Seward",
            "Seward’s Folly"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alaska governor who was nominated for the Vice Presidency in 2008.",
          "answer": "Sarah Palin"
        },
        {
          "question": "British navigator who visited Alaska as part of a series of voyages aboard the Endeavor.",
          "answer": "James Cook"
        },
        {
          "question": "plane crash.",
          "answer": "Ted Stevens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial capital of Alaska, the site of an 1804 battle against the Tlingit.",
          "answer": "Sitka"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the two Aleutian islands that were occupied by Japan during World War II.",
          "answer": "Attu and/or Kiska"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modern Terrorism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader of al-Qaeda who was killed in Pakistan in 2011.",
          "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Building complex in New York that was destroyed on 9/11.",
          "answer": [
            "World Trade Center or WTC",
            "Twin Towers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American detention camp in Cuba where terrorists have been interrogated.",
          "answer": "Guantanamo Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Member of al-Qaeda who was the “architect” of 9/11 and the 2002 Bali nightclub bombing; he was captured in 2003.",
          "answer": [
            "Khalid Sheikh Mohammed",
            "KSM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Form of water-based torture used by the US on members of al-Qaeda, including that 9/11 architect.",
          "answer": "waterboarding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bio-toxin that was mailed to multiple news outlets and political figures in 2001.",
          "answer": "anthrax"
        },
        {
          "question": "American naval destroyer that was attacked by suicide bombers while in port in Yemen in 2000.",
          "answer": "USS Cole"
        },
        {
          "question": "Al-Qaeda operative who attempted to light plastic explosives in his shoe on a plane in December 2001.",
          "answer": "Richard Reid"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Canadian Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Current Prime Minister, who protested Aung San Suu Kyi [chee]’s treatment of the Rohingya by revoking her honorary citizenship.",
          "answer": "Justin Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of the current Prime Minister, who served two terms as Prime Minister himself.",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who served until 2015, the first PM from the modern Conservative Party.",
          "answer": "Stephen Harper"
        },
        {
          "question": "First prime minister of Canada, who resigned over the Pacific Scandal.",
          "answer": "John A. Macdonald"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who resolved the Suez Canal Crisis and won a Nobel Peace Prize.",
          "answer": "Lester Pearson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister during World War II, the longest-serving PM in Canadian history.",
          "answer": "William Lyon Mackenzie King"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female Prime Minister, who served for just over four months after Brian Mulroney’s retirement.",
          "answer": "Kim Campbell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal Prime Minister who opposed conscription during World War I.",
          "answer": "Wilfrid Laurier"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mayans",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Technology whose “Long Count” type supposedly predicted the end of the world in 2012.",
          "answer": "calendar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prominent Mexican peninsula on which the Mayan civilization was centered.",
          "answer": "Yucatan Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan city where the Temple of Kukulcan, a massive step-pyramid, is found.",
          "answer": "Chichen Itza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious action carried out at a sinkhole called the Sacred Cenote to honor the rain god Chaac.",
          "answer": "human and/or child sacrifice"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mythological text of the K’iche people that describes the Hero Twins and was preserved by a Dominican friar.",
          "answer": "Popul Vuh"
        },
        {
          "question": "7th century Mayan ruler of Palenque who had the longest-known reign of any American ruler.",
          "answer": [
            "Pacal the Great",
            "Pacal I",
            "II",
            "8 Ahau",
            "Sun Shield"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan city in Guatemala’s Peten region, a rival of Calakmul and home of the Lost World complex.",
          "answer": [
            "Tikal",
            "Yax Mutal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Conquistador who helped conquer Mayan settlements before helping Cortes conquer the Aztecs and governing Guatemala.",
          "answer": "Pedro de Alvarado"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modern Asian Leaders",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "North Korean family that advocates Juche and includes Supreme Leader Jong-un.",
          "answer": "Kim family"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader who announced the One Belt, One Road Initiative as China’s current President.",
          "answer": "Xi Jinping"
        },
        {
          "question": "Successor of Manmohan Singh and BJP party leader who became Prime Minister in 2014.",
          "answer": "Narendra Modi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the National League for Democracy who won the 1991 Nobel Peace Prize under house arrest in Rangoon.",
          "answer": "Aung San Suu Kyi"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who resigned in 2019 and now lends his name to the capital of Kazakhstan.",
          "answer": "Nursultan Abishuly Nazarbayev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal Democratic Prime Minister whose economic policy is based on “three arrows.”",
          "answer": "Shinzo Abe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lebanese Prime Minister whose father’s 2005 assassination sparked the Cedar Revolution.",
          "answer": "Saad Hariri"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling family of Bhutan whose “Dragon King” Jigme Singye abdicated in 2006.",
          "answer": "Wangchuck family"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assassinations",
      "prompt": "Name the assassinations...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Target of Operation Neptune Spear and leader of al-Qaeda.",
          "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caribbean leader who the CIA supposedly failed to kill in 638 different ways, including exploding cigars.",
          "answer": "Fidel Castro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of ISIS until his 2019 death by suicide during the Barisha raid.",
          "answer": "Abu Bakr al-Baghdadi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the Quds Force who was assassinated at Baghdad Airport in January 2020.",
          "answer": "Qasem Soleimani"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of South Vietnam who was killed in a 1963 CIA-backed coup.",
          "answer": "Ngo Dinh Diem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Target of Operation Vengeance, a Japanese admiral whose plane was shot down in 1943.",
          "answer": "Isoroku Yamomoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caribbean leader known as “el Jefe” [el HAY-fay] who was ambushed by his own military in 1961.",
          "answer": "Rafael Trujillo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Member of al-Qaeda who became the first US citizen targeted by a drone strike without due process in 2011.",
          "answer": "Anwar Nasser al-Awlaki"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Afghanistan",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city, captured by the Northern Alliance in 2001.",
          "answer": "Kabul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling power in Afghanistan that was ousted in the 2001 US invasion.",
          "answer": [
            "Taliban",
            "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious figure that was the subject of two massive statues that were dynamited in Bamiyan by that group.",
          "answer": [
            "Buddha",
            "Siddhartha Gautama",
            "Bamiyan Buddhas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for US-backed Afghan guerrilla fighters during the Soviet invasion.",
          "answer": "mujahideen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Global organization, developed at the 1955 Bandung Conference, that it joined in 1961.",
          "answer": "Non-Aligned Movement"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was succeeded by Ashraf Ghani in 2014 after nearly 13 years in power.",
          "answer": "Hamid Karzai"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 1978 coup in which President Mohammed Daoud Khan and his family were murdered.",
          "answer": "Saur Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final King of Afghanistan, who was deposed in 1973.",
          "answer": "Mohammed Zahir Shah"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Peru",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Peru, where a 1996 embassy hostage crisis took place.",
          "answer": "Lima"
        },
        {
          "question": "Culture whose people created massive line drawings in the Peruvian desert soil.",
          "answer": [
            "Nazca people",
            "Nazca Lines"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician of Japanese descent who served as a corrupt president during the 1990s.",
          "answer": "Alberto Fujimori"
        },
        {
          "question": "Winner of the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature, who lost the 1990 presidential election.",
          "answer": "Mario Vargas Llosa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Communist guerrilla group that was fought by the government death squad Grupo Colina.",
          "answer": [
            "Communist Party of Peru - Shining Path",
            "Sendero Luminoso"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of that group; he was captured in 1992.",
          "answer": "Abimael Guzman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Sapa Inca, who was executed in 1572; an independence fighter in the 18th century and another guerrilla group took his name.",
          "answer": [
            "Tupac Amaru",
            "Jose Gabriel Tupac Amaru",
            "Tupac Amaru II",
            "Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Event being celebrated by the hostages when the embassy crisis began on December 17, 1996.",
          "answer": "Emperor Akihito’s birthday"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Aboriginal Australians",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Large rock formation in the Northern Territory considered sacred to the local Aboriginal people",
          "answer": [
            "Uluru",
            "Ayers Rock"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Annual event held on May 26th in which the government apologizes to the Aboriginal community",
          "answer": [
            "National Sorry Day",
            "National Day of Healing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas team for which Australian basketball player of Aboriginal heritage, Patty Mills, won a championship with Tim Duncan in 2014",
          "answer": [
            "San Antonio Spurs",
            "Spurs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kevin Rudd held this position when he offered an official apology to the Aboriginal people in 2008",
          "answer": "Prime Minister of the Commonwealth of Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native inhabitants of a group of islands north of the Cape York Peninsula which include the Mabuiag and Merian people",
          "answer": "Torres Strait Islanders"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term given to thousands of Aboriginal children who were kidnapped and rehomed over a period of 70 years",
          "answer": "Stolen Generation"
        },
        {
          "question": "1997 report created by Ronald Wilson and Mick Dodson which investigated that group of children",
          "answer": [
            "Bringing Them Home",
            "Report of the National Inquiry into the Separation of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Children from Their Families"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Decade-long strategy launched in 2008 to reduce disparity between Aboriginals and the rest of Australia",
          "answer": "Closing the Gap 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the assassination of archduke franz ferdinand, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Destructive global conflict which began as a result of the assassination",
          "answer": [
            "World War One or First World War",
            "The Great War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dual monarchy Franz Ferdinand helped lead as Archduke",
          "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who shot Franz Ferdinand after his driver made a wrong turn",
          "answer": "Gavrilo Princip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian nationalist organization that was implicated in the assassination",
          "answer": [
            "The Black Hand",
            "Unification",
            "Death"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Crisis sparked by the assassination during which Russia mobilized its armed forces",
          "answer": "July Crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who, despite hearing of the assassination, continued his spa vacation",
          "answer": "Franz Joseph I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of the archduke who was assassinated along with him",
          "answer": [
            "Sophie, Duchess of Hohenberg",
            "Sophie Chotek"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Crown Prince whose suicide in the Mayerling incident made Franz Ferdinand the heir apparent",
          "answer": "Rudolf 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The War on Terror",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. Defense headquarters building attacked in 2001",
          "answer": "The Pentagon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Al-Qaeda leader who took responsibility for that attack",
          "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where that man was found and killed during Operation Neptune Spear",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial 2001 act which allowed law enforcement to wiretap domestic phones without a warrant",
          "answer": "USA PATRIOT Act or Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phrase coined by George W. Bush in 2002 to describe state sponsors of terrorism including Iran, Iraq, and North Korea",
          "answer": "Axis of Evil"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. Navy destroyer that was attacked by a suicide bomber while in Yemen",
          "answer": "USS Cole"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who oversaw coalition forces in Iraq and later pled guilty to leaking confidential information to Paula Broadwell",
          "answer": "David Petraeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret department created by the DOD to oversee psychological operations",
          "answer": "Office of Strategic Influence"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the Philippines in the post-colonial era, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the philippines in the post-colonial era, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President elected in 2016 who has been criticized for his extremely harsh penalties against drug users",
          "answer": "Rodrigo Duterte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea it shares with Vietnam and Indonesia that has been the site of territorial disputes with a country that claims everything within a \"nine-dash line\"",
          "answer": "South China Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator who was forced to flee to Hawaii after being removed in a 1968 revolution",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who opposed that leader and whose assassination at Manilla International Airport led to massive protests",
          "answer": [
            "Benigno Aquino Jr",
            "Ninoy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Volcano that's 1991 eruption coincided with Typhoon Yunya, leading to hundreds of millions of dollars in damage",
          "answer": "Mount Pinatubo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second female president who served from 2001 to 2010",
          "answer": [
            "Gloria Macapagal Arroyo",
            "GMA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Peaceful protest that led to the resignation of Joseph Estrada in 2001",
          "answer": [
            "Second EDSA Revolution",
            "People Power Revolution II",
            "EDSA II",
            "EDSA 2001"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Armed militant group that broke away from the Moro Islamic Liberation Front under the leadership of Ameril Umbra Kato",
          "answer": [
            "Bangsamoro Islamic Freedom Fighters",
            "BIFF 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Zimbabwe",
      "prompt": "Concerning Zimbabwe, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Zimbabwe, known as Salisbury under British rule.",
          "answer": "Harare"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African people whose chief Mzilikazi established his personal kingdom in Zimbabwe following a rebellion against his kin, Shaka.",
          "answer": "Zulu or amaZulu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic effect experienced by the Zimbabwean dollar which led to its virtual abandonment in the 2000s.",
          "answer": "Hyperinflation"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Zimbabwe who ruled for thirty years beginning in 1980.",
          "answer": "Robert Mugabe or Robert Gabriel Mugabe"
        },
        {
          "question": "British businessman and owner of De Beers diamond company who once named Zimbabwe.",
          "answer": [
            "Cecil Rhodes or Cecil John Rhodes",
            "Rhodesia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Party which has ruled Zimbabwe since its independence.",
          "answer": "ZANU-PF"
        },
        {
          "question": "White prime minister of what is now Zimbabwe who fought communist-backed Black nationalist guerrillas during the Bush War.",
          "answer": "Ian Smith or Ian Douglas Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "1979 \"Agreement\" which ended the destructive Bush War, establishing an independent and Black-led Zimbabwe.",
          "answer": "Lancaster House Agreement"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the 1930s, this company ran a plantation in Brazil named after this company’s\nfounder. A group of young workers in this company nicknamed the Whiz Kids included\nRobert (20 pts) ",
        "McNamara. This company developed a program called “The Way Forward”\nafter former Boeing employee Alan Mulally was appointed CEO and became the only one\nof the Big (10 pts) ",
        "Three in its industry not to receive a bailout following the 2008 financial crisis.\nFor 10 points, name this automobile manufacturer that is part of that Big Three with Chrysler\nand General Motors."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ford Motor Company",
        "Ford"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A future holder of this position declared that “Ginger Rodgers did everything Fred Astaire did, just backwards in high heels” and said that another politician was “born with a silver foot in his mouth” during her keynote speech at the (20 pts)",
        "1988 DNC. Another governor of this state faced controversy over the implementation of the InnerChange Program and the (10 pts)",
        "execution of Karla Faye Tucker. That man defeated Ann Richards for this post and vacated this position after beating Al Gore in the presidential election of 2000. For 10 points, name this position held in the 1990s by George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas Governor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A hand position often taken by this person has been nicknamed this person’s “diamond” and the “Triangle of Power.” This person attacked a former mentor after the 1999 “black money affair.” This leader claimed that attempts to build a multicultural society had (20 pts)",
        "“utterly failed” in 2010. This leader’s government helped bail out Hypo Real Estate, and this Time Magazine (10 pts)",
        "2015 Person of the Year has agreed to allow an “open-door” policy with regards to Syrian refugees entering her country. For ten points, name this head of the Christian Democratic Union and current Chancellor of Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Angela Merkel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man controversially claimed that all dry cleaners were closed when Japan and South Korea played in the 2006 World Baseball Classic. One of Bill Simmons’ first columns for ESPN asked if this man was the Antichrist. In the (20 pts)",
        "2000 World Series, he threw a shattered bat in the direction of Mike Piazza. This player contradicted his former trainer, Brian McNamee, after having been implicated by the (10 pts)",
        "Mitchell Report. For ten points, name this retired pitcher who won seven Cy Young Awards with the Red Sox, Blue Jays, Yankees, and Astros, but only received 45% of Hall of Fame votes in 2016 amid claims of steroid use."
      ],
      "answer": "William Roger Clemens"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. These two universities co-founded edX, an online education platform, in 2012. Dr. Eric Lander, who published a controversial revisionist history of the development of CRISPR [”crisper”] DNA segments in January 2015, directs the (20 pts)",
        "Broad Institute, a collaboration between these two schools. These schools also collaborate in a Masters’ program between one’s Sloan School of Management and the other’s (10 pts)",
        "Kennedy School of Government. For ten points, name these two universities, both located on the north side of the Charles River in Cambridge, Massachusetts."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Harvard University and Massachusetts Institute of Technology or MIT",
        "in either order",
        "prompt if only one is given"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man claimed that using body doubles as a security measure was “movie magic, not reality” in a conversation with George Piro. Piro’s interrogation of this man, described as “High Value Detainee #1,” found he held (20 pts)",
        "no links with al-Qaeda or interest in creating an Islamic state. Nine months after a “shock and awe” campaign began, this man was discovered in a (10 pts)",
        "“spider hole” on a farm near Tikrit in December 2003. For ten points, name this Ba’ath Party leader who was hanged in December 2006 for crimes against humanity carried out as President of Iraq."
      ],
      "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. The 2006 film Long Road to Heaven describes this event and the ensuing trials of Amrozi and Imam Samudri, who were executed in 2008 for their roles in it. One part of this event was allegedly triggered by Dulmatin’s (20 pts)",
        "cell phone. A group led by Riduan Isamuddin perpetrated this event, in which a Mitsubishi L300 loaded with C4 was detonated outside Paddy’s Pub and the (10 pts)",
        "Sari Club. Over 200 people were killed in this event, which was carried out by members of Jemaah Islamiyah, a terrorist group based in Southeast Asia. For ten points, name this 2002 bombing, the deadliest terrorist attack in Indonesian history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "2002 Bali bombing",
        "other descriptors"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Van Orden sued this state in 2002 to take down a display of the Ten Commandments; the case was argued at the Supreme Court by this state’s Attorney General, who became Governor after defeating pro-choice State Senator Wendy (20 pts)",
        "Davis in 2014. The previous governor of this state currently serves as head of the Department of Energy, a department that he proposed to eliminate in his 2012 presidential bid. Another former governor of this state promoted the (10 pts)",
        "No Child Left Behind Act after he was elected president in 2000. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by Greg Abbott, Rick Perry, and George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these documents claims found that a Swiss lawyer named Dieter Neupert was directly in contact with the Royal family of Qatar. A reporter for the Munich-based publication SZ broke the story about these documents, some of which focused on (20 pts)",
        "Sigmundur Gunnlaugson of Iceland. The law firm Mossack Fonseca created these documents, whose revelation prompted David (10 pts)",
        "Cameron to admit that he profited from offshore accounts held by his father. For ten points, name this set of over 11 million documents that were leaked in 2016 and linked illegal shell companies to prominent figures."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama Papers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One politician with this surname was the target of a foiled coup attempt, Operation Midnight Jackal, and her husband earned the label “Mr. Ten Percent” for receiving government kickbacks. Another leader with this surname declared that his country would obtain a (20 pts)",
        "nuclear weapon “even if we have to eat grass” and refused to recognize the Awami League; that politician was deposed by Zia al-Huq in Operation Fair Play. A woman with this surname was (10 pts)",
        "assassinated in 2008 by a suicide bomber while on the campaign trail. For ten points, name this surname held by two former prime ministers of Pakistan, Zulfikar and Benazir."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bhutto family",
        "Benazir and/or Zulfikar Ali Bhutto"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a parody of this show on Cheers, Cliff Clavin complains that Cary Grant really had never been in his kitchen. An SNL skit parodying this show featured Tom Hanks playing a MAGA hat-wearing character who bonds with Kenan Thompson, playing the (20 pts)",
        "host. In another take on this show, H&R Block, not FedEx, was a correct answer that ended a (10 pts)",
        "74-game winning streak on this show in 2004. Art Fleming originally hosted this show, which removed its five-win cap in 2003 before Ken Jennings’ record run. For ten points, name this syndicated game show hosted by Alex Trebek."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jeopardy!",
        "Black Jeopardy!"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard Gott resigned from an editorial post for this publication after being accused of secretly negotiating with the KGB. Sarah Tisdall leaked information about the positioning of cruise missiles to this publication, which controversially defended the Widgery Tribunal in the aftermath of (20 pts)",
        "Bloody Sunday. David Cameron’s role in the Panama Papers was investigated by this newspaper, which broke the news of NSA surveillance programs leaked by (10 pts)",
        "Edward Snowden in 2013. The Observer is the sister newspaper to, for ten points, what British daily newspaper that was founded in Manchester and revealed the 2011 News phone hacking scandal?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Manchester Guardian"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This political family granted asylum to Alois Brunner, a Nazi who probably died in their home country in 2010. The coup d’etat that brought this family to power shares its name with an Egyptian movement a year later; this family’s Corrective Revolution purged followers of (20 pts)",
        "Salah Jadid from the country’s Baath Party. The current head of this Alawite family is overseeing a nine year long (10 pts)",
        "civil war that broke out during the Arab Spring. For ten points, name this family whose members, including Hafez and Bashar, have controlled the Syria for nearly five decades."
      ],
      "answer": "al-Assad family"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This project’s employees included Lilli Hornig, who was initially given typist orientation instructions. Maria Goeppert Mayer won a Nobel Prize for her work done with this project. Leona Libby, a grad student at the University of Chicago, helped construct an experiment at (20 pts)",
        "Stagg Field for this project. Lise Meitner refused to work on this project, the subject of a 2014 book by Denise Kiernan about women brought to (10 pts)",
        "Oak Ridge, Tennessee. Chien-Shiung Wu provided troubleshooting advice to Enrico Fermi about neutron poisoning for, for ten points, what military research project, the subject of Kiernan’s The Girls of Atomic City, that produced the first atomic bombs?"
      ],
      "answer": "Manhattan Project"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A classic image of this figure may have been modeled on a photo of Naomi Parker which has been misattributed as Geraldine Hoff. J. Howard Miller was hired to create that image of this figure for (20 pts)",
        "Westinghouse Electric. Based on actual people working in historically male-dominated jobs, much like \"Wendy the Welder,\" this figure was depicted wearing a (10 pts)",
        "red bandana and flexing her arm in a poster which read \"We Can Do It!\" Norman Rockwell popularized, for ten points, what female icon, modeled on real factory workers during World War Two?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rosie the Riveter 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This group was founded by William Ireland, Aaron Grosh and Oliver Kelley. Wisconsin passed a strict rate-fixing law based on this group's advocacy called the Potter Law, which stopped all railroad construction in the state. (*) Certain consumers were offered goods through Montgomery Ward, which associated itself with this organization which spurned the Munn v. Illinois decision and created (*) Rural Free Delivery. For ten points, name this fraternal agricultural organization popular after the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Grange",
        "The National Grange of the Order of Patrons of Husbandry 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A company owned by this man inspired the term \"red carpet treatment\" for its treatment of customers. This man's company operated the Water Level Route and the High Line, which is now a park. Grand Central Depot was built by this man for his New York (*) Central Railroad, and this man opposed Daniel Drew's takeover of the Erie Railroad. This man's career began working for steamboat owner Thomas Gibbons of Gibbons v. Ogden fame. The original benefactor to a namesake (*) university in Nashville, for ten points, who was this railroad magnate \"Commodore\"?"
      ],
      "answer": "Cornelius Vanderbilt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The tradition of building rectangular \"paradise\" examples of these locations dates back to the Achaemenid [ah-keh-MEE-nid]] Empire. While fleeing Persia, Baha'u'llah stayed at one of these locations in Baghdad named Ridván. Before the (20 pts)",
        "crucifixion, Jesus sweat drops of blood in one of these locations named Gethsemane. The confluence of the Tigris and the Euphrates is described as the location of one of these places in the (10 pts)",
        "book of Genesis. For ten points, name this type of location, one of which named Eden was where God created the first humans."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Garden",
        "Garden of Eden",
        "Garden of Gethsemane 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The persecuted Hazaras minority group opposed this group by joining the Northern Alliance led by deposed president Burhanuddin Rabbani. This organization’s leader, Mohammed Omar, ordered the destruction of the giant (20 pts)",
        "Buddha statues of Bamiyan in 2001. This Sunni regime, which succeeded the Mujahideen, combined Pashtun cultural norms with a draconic interpretation of (10 pts)",
        "Sharia [[SHAH-REE-AH]] law. For ten points, name this fundamentalist group which controlled Afghanistan from 1996 until it was overthrown by the 2001 U.S. invasion."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Taliban",
        "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan",
        "IEA 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the aftermath of this event, Henry Garnet was killed for refusing to break the confidentiality of confession. Francis Tresham may have sent a letter to William Parker which revealed the plans for this event. The leaders of this event had earlier raided (20 pts)",
        "Warwick Castle, a move that led Richard Walsh to corner them at the Holbeche House. The perpetrators of this event hoped to usher in a Catholic state by putting Elizabeth (10 pts)",
        "Stuart on the throne. James I was targeted in, for ten points, what plot in which Guy Fawkes attempted to blow up the House of Lords?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder Treason Plot",
        "the Jesuit Treason 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's sister, Claire, was the first social scientist hired by Oak Ridge National Laboratory. The anti-nuclear Critical Mass Energy Project was created by this man who is central to the documentary An Unreasonable Man. This man coined the term (20 pts)",
        "\"Corporate welfare\" and was serving as an unpaid consultant to Abe Ribicoff when he inspired a Traffic and Motor Vehicle law. To evaluate the FTC, this man created a group of seven law students called his (10 pts)",
        "\"Raiders.\" For ten points, name this consumer advocate who wrote Unsafe at Any Speed."
      ],
      "answer": "Ralph Nader 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This son of a former Ambassador to Hungary facilitated the rearmament of Israel with Iron Dome Surface-to-Air Missiles during the 2014 Gaza conflict. On his first day in office, this Cabinet member froze all arms sales to (20 pts)",
        "Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates. During his confirmation hearing, this politician promised to continue recognition of (10 pts)",
        "Jerusalem as the capital of Israel rather than returning the U.S. embassy to Tel Aviv. For ten points, name this Secretary of State in the Biden administration."
      ],
      "answer": "Antony Blinken"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his early education at Amasya under the tutoring of Akshamsaddin, this man was influenced to fulfill his Islamic duty. Portugal sent an expedition to fight this man at the request of Sixtus IV, in which 800 men led by Antonio Primaldi were taken to the Hill of Minerva to be executed as martyrs at (20 pts)",
        "Otranto. Besides Italy, this man defeated Skanderbeg in Albania and defeated John Hunyadi after the Peace of Szeged was broken. In (10 pts)",
        "1453, this man ended the Byzantine Empire by conquering Constantinople. For ten points, name this Ottoman Sultan."
      ],
      "answer": "Mehmed II or Mehmed the Conqueror 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was named \"The Red King\" and Mormaer [[MORE-mare]] of Moray after the death of a man nicknamed \"the Unfortunate.\" After fighting Godwin of Essex, this man who introduced feudalism to (20 pts)",
        "Scotland, was killed at the Battle of Lumphanan [[loom-FAH-nahn]] and was succeeded by Lulach [[LOO-lock]], who was killed by Malcolm III. Raphael Holinshed's [[HALL-in-sheds]] works inspired a (10 pts)",
        "playwright to tell this man's story which included the Three Witches. For ten points, name this man who is killed by MacDuff in Shakespeare's rendition of the story of this ill-fated king."
      ],
      "answer": "Macbeth or Mac Bethad mac Findlaích 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2017, this state's officials brought in Irula tribesmen from the Indian subcontinent to capture invasive Burmese Pythons. Since the 1990s, a landfill in the south of this state has been piled over with soil to avoid odors, leading to the affectionate nickname \"Mount Trashmore.\" Lake (20 pts)",
        "Hell 'n Blazes is the source of this state's St. Johns River, which hosted the indigenous Timucua people as well as settlements of this state's namesake \"Crackers.\" (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this Southern state known in the 2010s for a namesake \"man\" who commits unusual crimes in places like the Everglades."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Florida",
        "Florida Man"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Frauke Petry resigned from this party in favor of forming her own Blue Party, which dissolved following a 0.1 percent vote in Thuringia's general election. André Poggenburg was ousted from this party after publicly calling Turkish (20 pts)",
        "immigrants \"fatherless vermin.\" Björn Höcke [[HYOO-kuh]], a leader of this party, was accused of anti-Semitism after criticizing the existence of the Holocaust Memorial in (10 pts)",
        "Berlin as a \"Memorial of Shame.\" For ten points, name this populist right-wing party founded in 2013 in Lower Saxony."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alternative for Germany",
        "Alternative für Deutschland",
        "or AdF"
      ]
    }
  ]
}